Guide to the Board of Trustees records, 1821-2003 RG0001
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
- Committees, 1911-1960; RG0001 Series 5; 4 Linear feet (Box 1, Box 2, Box 3, Box 4, Box 5, Box 6, Box 7, Box 8)
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 07/01/1958 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    Text on folder "Discussion of the Hospital policy in reference to discounts. A complete statement of the present discount policy was requested by the Committee; Approval of an increase in a month;y beginning salary from $270 to $290 for graduate nurses; Discussion of 2 proposals for expanding facilities of Medical Center: the building of new wing on the Hospital for which the University had received $200,000 from the Ford Foundation, the purchase of the Keystone Apartments. No recommendation was made. President Marvin said the decision should be made by the Board; Treasurer Herzog was asked to find out if the Keystone is still available and to secure an estimate of the cost and method of financing the purchase and also secure data on cost of remodeling part of the building for new uses; The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/28/1958 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    Text on folder "Approval by the Committee of the following: A Resident in Neurology effective July 1, 1958; Purchase of new bedside tables for the hospital at cost of $18,000; Refinishing of hospital furniture in patients' rooms. This is not to exceed $10,000 for first year. Contract with Group Hospitalization, Inc.; Relationship between the George Washington University Cancer Clinic and the Hospital discussed. It was the feeling of the Committee the Hospital and clinic should be brought as closely together as possible in administration; The Committee adjourned at 2:20 o'clock."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/05/1956 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    Text on folder "Executive Committee of the Hospital Staff met with the Committee to consider plans for making application for the Ford Foundation grant of $226,500: Discussion about need for a new medical school building; Need for expansion of the Hospital - laboratories, Pediatrics, etc.; 4-story addition to the Hospital vs. a smaller addition for the present; Competition with Children's Hospital if Dept. of Pediatrics is established; Recommendations to be made to the Board of Trustees regarding use of the funds, with a 250,000 cubic foot addition at a cost of not more than $500,000."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/02/1956 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    Text on Folder "Approval for Executive Committee of Hospital to be invited to meet with the Board Committee from time to time; Discussion concerning Ford Foundation Grant Application; Approval of expansion of service in Pathology to include Clinical Pathologist. (Would replace Dr. Choisse on Medical School staff); Proposal to study possibility of affiliation with Children's Hospital for Pediatric Service; Passed over expansion of Neurosurgery and Psychiatry; Number of interns and residents not to be increased unless more staff beds could be provided; Report of American Hospital Assn. and Assn. of American Medical Schools relative to perquisites to be obtained; Reopening of the union contract and possible wage increases. Referred to Committee on Bldgs. and Lands: Additional wing for expanded work in Pathology and other laboratories, office space for professional staff and Business Offices; Problem of space for lockers, records, and laundry; Possibility of building parking ramp in Square 55. Discussion of Out Patient Dept. To see if Mellon gift precludes transfer out of the Hospital building; Air conditioning - possibility of use of room units; Iowa Court Decision re revenues from laboratories and ex-ray service; Discussion of Medical Director of the Hospital upon the retirement of Dean Bloedorn; Working capital of Hospital. Study to be made to see how other hospitals stand in accounts receivable; Discussion of building funds under Law221 and Hill-Burton Act."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/21/1955 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    Text on folder "Reason for establishment of Committee. Approval to invite University and Hospital staff to meet with Committee at request of President; Financial situation - Sept. - Nov. '54; Remodeling of second floor of Out Patient Department. Approved. Report on Hospital salaries to see if space should be provided; Refurnishing 5 private rooms. Approved; Additional Resident in Surgery approved; Additional Junior Resident in Obstetrics approved; Rehabilitation program discussed; Purchase of diagnostic X-Ray Unit and Rotational attachment for Picker Therapy machine for Dept. of Radiology; Report on all special services in Hospital asked for; Air conditioning discussed."
  - Committee on the University Hospital--correspondence and meeting minutes, Correspondence, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/30/1961 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    Text on folder "The Committee met to consider what further action, if any, should be taken with respect to the University's appeals to the Armed Services Board of Contract Appeals from disallowances of claims for indirect costs under 3 cost-reimbursement type contracts between the University and the Dept. of the Army. Summary of the issues presented to the Committee. The Committee voted to accept the decision. The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 11/24/1958 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    Text on folder "Discussion of an offer of $200 for scholarship aid for Negro students. It was felt in light of social trends any scholarship accepted should not carry racial restrictions. The University has 2 scholarships restricted to the white race; the committee felt hereafter it wold not be desirable to accept scholarships with racial restrictions; however, no attempt should be made to alter the terms of scholarships previously accepted. The above scholarship will be offered without restrictions; approval of trustees' fees on portion of testamentary trust in the Clarence W. DeKnight Estate (3% by American Security and Trust Company and 3% by Mr. Frank Nesibitt). The committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 12/07/1956 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    Text on folder "Recommendation that Mr. F. Elwood Davis be named as University Counsel to replace Trustee Cummings, deceased; Powell and Swisher Scholarship Funds to be referred to University counsel. Income from these funds cannot be used for the purposes specified in the bequests."
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/16/1940 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    Text on folder "Questionnaire from Att'y General on Hospital"
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 01/30/1933 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    Text on folder "Re: Letter from American Pharmaceutical Association; Letter from Mr. Paul Rogers; Notes of Chas. Henry Butler; Tax - Addie Sanders Estate"
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, 03/14/1930 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - Committee on Legal Affairs--correspondence and meeting minutes, University Legal Council, correspondence, 1956 -1957 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Committee on University Libraries and Museums--minute meetings, 11/29/1955 (Box 8, Folder 18)
    Text on folder "Discussion of Middle States Association Evaluation Report concerning Library and Library facilities; Recommendation #2 of MSA Report was to be brought to Board of Trustees for consideration following survey by Faculty Library Committee; Recommendation #6 of MSA Report was referred to Faculty Library Committee."
  - Committee on University Libraries and Museums--minute meetings, 10/06/1955 (Box 8, Folder 19)
    Text on folder "Recommended to the Board: Adoption of Statement of Library Policy; Treasurer to be authorized to deputize library personnel to collect fines for books held overtime; Consideration of Report of Faculty Library Committee; Library Housing and Facilities; Approval for President to Purchase "Port-Hole" Portrait of George Washington by Rembrandt Peale."
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, Correspondence, 1950 -1960 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, Alumni Nominations of Trustees, 1952 -1963 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, Blank Ballots, undated (Box 8, Folder 22)
    Text on Folder "For Election of Trustees"
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/28/1958 (Box 8, Folder 23)
    Text on folder "The Committee accepted nomination of the following alumni for membership in the Class of 1961 Board of Trustees: Watson Davis, Frederick August Reuter; Recommendation that the above Alumni Trustees be presented to the Board along with other Charter Trustees whose terms expire; Recommendation of the following persons for Board of Trustees membership: Class of 1959: R. Roy Dunn, Philip L. Graham, Carleton D. Smith, L. Corrin Strong; Class of 1960: Leonard Carmichael; Class of 1961: Watson W. Wise; There were no minutes taken at this meeting"
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/18/1957 (Box 8, Folder 24)
    Text on Folder "Recommendation to Board that Sidney William Souers be placed in nomination for Class of 1959; Recommendation to approach the following persons for consideration as Board Members: Wiley Buchanan, Mr. Justice Harlan, Edward Karrick Morris, Samuel Spencer"
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/06/1957 (Box 8, Folder 25)
    Text on folder "The Committee accepted nomination of following alumni for membership in the Class of 1960 Board of Trustees - Brooks Hays, George Edward Muth; Recommendation that the above Alumni Trustees be presented to the Board along with other Charter Trustees whose terms expire; Recommendation that Trustee James Matlack Mitchell be added to the list of Charter Trustees for Class of 1960; Recommendation of the following persons for Board of Trustees membership, class of 1958: Edward Karrick Morris, Samuel Spencer; Class of 1959: Wiley Buchanan; Recommendation to the Board to amend Chapter I of the By-Laws, adding a new Section 6 creating the status of Honorary Trustees; The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/10/1956 (Box 8, Folder 26)
    Text on folder "Membership in Class of 1959 Alumni Nominations: Dr. Daniel L. Borden, Miss Helen Newman; Charter Trustees: Nomination of all whose terms expire except Trustee Evan Howell whose attendance record was considered by the Committee."
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/19/1955 (Box 8, Folder 27)
    Text on folder "Membership in Class of 1958; Chairman to draft statement on standards applying to those considered for membership on the Board."
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 02/10/1955 (Box 8, Folder 28)
    Text on folder "Recommendation that Mr. Godfrey L. Munter be considered as third member from National University to serve on the Board of Trustees of The George Washington University."
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/13/1954 (Box 8, Folder 29)
    Text on folder "Alumni nominations for Class of 1957; Nominations for Trustees of Class of 1957"
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/22/1952 (Box 8, Folder 30)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 04/14/1950 (Box 8, Folder 31)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/19/1949 (Box 8, Folder 32)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/27/1943 (Box 8, Folder 33)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 05/29/1942 (Box 8, Folder 34)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/03/1941 (Box 8, Folder 35)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/04/1940 (Box 8, Folder 36)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 10/13/1938 (Box 8, Folder 37)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/01/1937 (Box 8, Folder 38)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, 06/04/1936 (Box 8, Folder 39)
  - Committee of Nominations--correspondence and meeting minutes, Votes of Trustees, 1935 (Box 8, Folder 40)
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 10/10/1960 (Box 8, Folder 41)
    Text on folder "Approval of Personnel Changes; The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 05/09/1960 (Box 8, Folder 42)
    Text on folder "The Committee voted to recommend to the Board that no further consideration of the Reichard matter was justified; that the University should employ counsel to consult with respect to letters from ACLU and AAUP; that replies to these letters be signed by Acting President of the University after consultation with counsel and further consideration by the Personnel Committee; Personnel changes approved; The Committee adjourned"
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 02/11/1960 (Box 8, Folder 43)
    Text on folder "Consideration of letters from Prof. Pollitt and Dr. Reichard. The Committee voted to recommend no further action be taken by the Board with respect to the withdrawal of Dr. Reichard's appointment and that Prof. Pollittt be advised the Board found no basis for further action; The Committee reviewed personnel changes and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees."
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 12/10/1959 (Box 8, Folder 44)
    Text on folder "The Committee reviewed personnel changes and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees; The Committee voted to approve the report and recommendation concerning Dr. Richard Wilson Reichard and recommend its favorable consideration; The Committee adjourned."
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 10/02/1959 (Box 8, Folder 45)
    Text on folder "Consideration of qualifications and suitability of Dr. Richard W. Reichard to join the faculty of the University. It was unanimously decided that Dr. Reichard would be offered the opportunity to appear before the Committee on Personnel; The Committee reviewed personnel changes and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees."
  - Committee on Personnel--meeting minutes, 05/06/1959 (Box 8, Folder 46)
    Text on folder "The Committee reviewed the personnel changes recommended by the appropriate officers and deans, and the Acting President, and voted to recommend their favorable consideration by the Board of Trustees."
- Congressional documents, 1826-1977; RG0001 Series 6; 1 Linear feet (Box 2, Box 1)
  This series is a collection of Congressional documents and related materials regarding The George Washington University and its predecessors. They range in date from 1826 to 1977.
  - Memorials of Sundry Citizens of the District of Columbia, 1826 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Excerpts from Various Issues of the Register of Debates in Congress about a Bill to Exempt President, Professors, Tutors, Stewards, and Students of Columbian College, 02/26/1825 (18th Congress, 2nd Session), April 20, 26-28, 1826 (19th Congress, 1st Session), (NOT Original), 1825 -1826 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Senate Report (No. 103) on a Bill for the Relief of Columbian College (20th Congress, 1st Session), (in an envelope), 02/14/1828 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Discussion of the Above Bill by Thomas L. McKenny, a Letter to the Editor of the National Intelligencer, (a photocopy), 02/18/1828 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Report (No. 290) of the Hose Committee for the District of Columbia on the Memorial of Robert B. Semple, President of the Board of Trustees of the Columbian College (21st Congress, 1st Session), (one is photocopy and the other is original in an envelope), 03/12/1830 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letter on the Request to Congress of a Grant of City Lots to Columbian College (handwritten original), 12/23/1930 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Report (No. 334) of the House Committee for the District of Columbia on the Request to Congress of a Donation (22nd Congress, 1st Session), (2 copies), 02/27/1832 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Letter from the Geneva College, New York, to the the Columbian College, Asking any Suggestion on the College's Memorial (Attached) to Congress Requesting a Grant, 03/19/1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Petitions to Congress for a Grant of Public Lands or Other Financial Assistance from the Federal Government, circa 1850 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Senate Report (No. 429) to Accompany S.1202 That Would Establish the University of United States, Dated March 10, 1896, (54th Congress, 1st Session). December 11 - Senate Report (No. 945) to Accompany S.3943 That Would Establish the University of United States, Dated April 1, 1902, (57th Congress, 1st Session), (2 copies, one is in an envelope), 1896 -1902 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Act to Amend the Charter of Columbian College, Public Law No. 7, 01/23/1904 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Act to Amend the Charter of Columbian College, Public Law No. 200 (2 original copies, one of which has missing pages; one is photocopy), 03/03/1905 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Appeal to the Senate in Behalf of Proposed University of United States made by Mr. Frye (Document No. 143, 60th Congress, 1st Session), 12/19/1907 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Report of a Conference on the University of United States, (2 copies), 06/22/1908 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Senate Report (No. 1083) on S.8819 That Would Admit the District of Columbia the Benefits of the Morrill Acts (6 copies), 02/24/1909 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brief Submitted by the George Washington University to the Senate Regarding S.8819 (3 different versions), 02/1909 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Petition Submitted by the George Washington University to Congress Regarding Gallinger Amendment to the Morrill Acts (S.530, 61st Congress (5 copies), 03/22/1909 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brief Statement of the Case Submitted by the George Washington University to the Senate Regarding S.530, (3 copies), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Petition Submitted by the George Washington University to Congress Regarding S.530 (7 copies), 12/08/1909 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Senate Report (No.220) on S.530, 02/14/1910 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - House Report (No.1003) on H.R.24316 Regarding the Extension of the Benefits of the Morrill Acts to the District of Columbia, 04/13/1910 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Brief Submitted by Richard Harlan, GW President, to Congress on the Bill (S.530) to Amend the Morrill Acts (3 copies), April 15, 1910; Brief About Tuition Subsidy; Brief to Argue Against President James of the Illinois University who Opposed to the Extension of the Benefits of the Morrill Acts to the District of Columbia (i.e., GW), undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Brief Collecting the Opinions of University Presidents Who Supported the Bill (S.530); Brief Explaining the Status of GW, Regarding the Gallinger-Boutell Bill (S.530, H.R.12343, 61st Congress), 04/15/1910 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Congressional Record, Including the Speech of Hon. Henry S. Boutell About GW (3 copies), 04/25/1910 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Attorney-General Report of an Investigation of the Financial and Educational Affairs of the George Washington University, Dated June 2, 1910, Followed by a House Resolution Regarding the Bill H.R.24316 to Extend the Benefits of the Morrill Acts to GW (3 copies), undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Attorney-General's Final Report on the Financial Condition of the George Washington University (3 copies), 12/06/1910 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Hearings Reports on the National University Bill (H.R.11749), Nos.4-9, 11 (pp.121-359, 383-425), 1914 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Senate Report (No.391) on the Bill S.4316 to Regulate the Use of Public School Buildings and Grounds in the District of Columbia, 03/30/1914 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Senate Report (No.36) on the Building as a Point of Interest in the National Capital, at which the Sino-Soviet Institute were located and torn down in February 1970, (65th Congress, 1st Session), NOT Original, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Hearing Report Entitled the Investigation of Students for a Democratic Society (SDS), Part 3-A, George Washington University, 07/22/1969 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Hearing Report (No.95-8) on the George Washington University Charter Restatement (H.R.2700, H.R.7300, and S.1060, 95th Congress), 1977 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Faculty, 1903-1909; RG0001 Series 7; 0.25 Linear feet
  This series is a collection of appointments and salaries of faculty. They range in date from 1903 to 1909.
  - Appointments and Salaries of Faculty, 1903 -1909 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Records, 1899-2003; RG0001 Series 8; 0.5 Linear feet (Box 1)
  This series contains correspondence, by-laws, notices, pamphlets, a report, and a memorandum. They range in date from 1899 to 2003. The materials concern the Committee on Student Affairs, non-academic student discipline, and other affairs.
  - Board of Trustees, 1902 -1992 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Board of Trustees - Charter, Ordinances and By-laws of the Columbian University, 5/31/1899 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Trustees-Chronological List of Members and Officers of Administration, 1821-2003, 1967 -2003 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Board of Trustees-Individuals-Bunker, George, 1982 -1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Board of Trustees-Individuals-Lisner, Abram, 1937 -1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Judicial System for Non-Academic Student Discipline, 1/22/1971 --3/18/1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Code and Ordinances Governing the Academic Personnel of the university, 1964; Series 8 (Box SHARED 2, Folder 3)